Section 8.7 weak to strong Historically,
much of the
work on AI alignment has been highly
theoretical, focusing
on foundational aspects of agent behavior,
inner alignment and
risks from learned optimization. Even the
techniques that we
talked about in previous sections like
Debate or IDA
are often criticized for being frameworks
rather than practical
solutions or mainly working on toy
problems without addressing
the core challenge of aligning
superintelligent AI in real
world scenarios. So even though we can
only conduct
safety experiments on current generation
models, how can we
be sure that these techniques will remain
effective as
AI's approach superhuman capabilities
Narrowly superhuman models allow case
studies of scalable oversight. Current day
models are good
enough at fuzzy tasks enough to be better
than
humans in some domains, but crucially they
are still
not better than all humans or superhuman
enough that
we cannot generate ground truth labels.
These types of
models are sometimes called narrowly
superhuman. This distinction between
narrowly superhuman and superhuman is very
important. As an
example of this difference, AlphaGo is
superhuman in the
sense that it beat Lee Sedol, making it
better
than every single human alive, whereas
GPT4 is still
only capable of writing text better than
some humans
but not all humans. This means that we can
use narrowly superhuman AIs as case
studies. We can
use either experts or the ground truth
labels that
we still have access to and see if
alignment
increases when we use our scalable
oversight techniques. The
core intuition here is to simulate future
scenarios where
humanity equipped with various tools and
techniques oversees the
outputs of untrustworthy but superhuman
systems. There are various
ways to conduct experiments on narrowly
superhuman models. We
can use non experts equipped with scalable
oversight techniques
to align AI models. Another way is to use
weak models, for example to represent
humans, while stronger
models, for example, represent more
capable AI systems that
we want to align. Stronger models are
expected to
have latent capabilities. The assumption
is that stronger models,
due to their extensive pre training on
diverse data,
already have internal representations for
the type of actions
we want. The role of weak supervision is
to
bring out this behavior through training
signals. As a
concrete example, imagine using GPT4 for
getting medical advice.
It has read countless research papers and
medical journals.
It has internal representations of a lot
of good
medical information, making it
theoretically capable of giving highly
competent medical advice. But GPTs are
initially only designed
to predict the most likely next word, not
give
accurate advice. In this context, aligning
the model means
getting the model to give accurate and
helpful medical
advice. One type of technique we can try
is
fine tuning GPT4 on labels generated by
GPT2. It's
not the only way. There are other
techniques that
we will explore later in this section. For
now,
the most important thing to understand is
that we
are currently operating under the
assumption that both current
and future superhuman models will will
likely have salient
internal representations of human
behaviors. What is weak to
Strong generalization? Weak supervision
involves training AI models using
labels or feedback that are less accurate,
less detailed
or noisier than those provided by highly
knowledgeable or
capable supervisors. This can happen when
supervisors, whether humans
or weaker models, are not experts in the
task
or when the data is incomplete or contains
errors.
At this point, the textbook shows Figure
8.22. It
depicts weak to strong generalization
eliciting strong capabilities with
weak supervision. Burns et al. 2023. Weak
to strong
generalization W2SG is when a strong model
trained with
weak supervision manages to outperform its
weak supervisor by
leveraging its pre existing knowledge and
capabilities. The core
idea is that the strong model already
possesses the
necessary capabilities for the desired
behavior and the weak
supervision elicits this behavior despite
its imperfections. The process
of W2SG right now typically begins by fine
tuning
a large pre trained model using weak
supervision from
smaller models. Although the initial
supervision may come from
these less capable models, the ultimate
aim is to
transition to human supervision. The
objective is to bring
out the strong model's full potential as
if it
were trained on perfect ground truth
supervision Burns itente
al. 2023. In current experiments, the
setup an a
weak supervisor a small pre trained
language model is
fine tuned on a specific task generating
predictions soft
labels on a held out data set a strong
student a larger pre trained LM is fine
tuned
on the weak model's predictions. A strong
ceiling, another
copy of the larger model is fine tuned
directly
on ground truth labels. For baseline
comparison, the level
of weak to strong generalization is
quantified using performance
gap recovered. PGR measures how much of
the performance
difference between a weak supervisor and a
strong model
is bridged when the strong model is
trained using
weak supervision. When we train the strong
model using
the labels provided by the weak model, the
performance
of the strong model will likely be
somewhere between
the performance of the weak model and the
ideal
performance the strong model could achieve
with perfect labels.
The performance gap recovered quantifies
how much closer the
strong model's performance gets to its
ideal performance compared
to the weak model's performance. A PGR of
corresponds to an ideal outcome. The
strong model performs
just as well as it would have with perfect
supervision. In contrast, a strong student
who succeeds in
perfectly imitating their supervisor,
including their flaws would obtain
a PGR of 0. Pgrach Text Student Paxt Posh
Week Text Ceiling R textend Alignment
Limitations and disanalogies
of W2SG overfitting to weak Supervision
the assumption that
a strong model will generalize well from
weak supervision
is not guaranteed. Superhuman models might
easily imitate weak
errors. These models will likely be very
proficient at
predicting what humans will think and say,
especially if
they are trained on human data.
Consequently, if we
naively train such a superhuman model with
human supervision,
it might simply imitate the weak
supervisor outputting human
level capabilities rather than its latent
superhuman capabilities. Researchers
also use auxiliary confidence losses which
encourage the strong
model to make confident predictions even
when contradicting the
weak supervision, promoting generalization
and correcting weak supervisor mistakes.
Assumptions about task representations
W2SG assumes that strong models
have salient representations of the tasks
they are trained
on. This means the models already possess
some understanding
of these tasks from their pre training
phase. However,
this assumption may not hold true for
novel or
highly complex tasks. If a task is
entirely new
or significantly more complex than what
the model has
encountered during pre training, the model
might not have
the latent capabilities necessary to
perform well even with
weak supervision. The experiments on W2SG
so far may
have been observed in pre training at
least indirectly.
Using the example from earlier medical
data or direct
questions and answers about medical
practice is present in
the GPT4 pre training dataset in some
form. However,
future superhuman models may never
directly observe superhuman alignment
relevant capabilities, which means these
types of capabilities might
be harder to elicit than capabilities that
models could
have observed in their pre training data.
This disanalogy
could cause current results on W2SG to be
overly
optimistic. Slow takeoff assumption W2SG
also relies on the
assumption of a gradual takeoff in AI
capabilities. This
gradual progression allows researchers
enough time to use moderately
superhuman models to solve alignment
problems iteratively before it's
too late. The window of opportunity
provided by a
gradual takeoff is crucial for refining
and testing alignment
techniques. W2SG can be seen as a
complement to
scalable oversight techniques. W2SG is not
a complete solution
even if a model generalizes in the desired
direction.
This must be verified, requiring a ground
truth signal
more reliable than naive human
supervision. By integrating W2SG
with scalable oversight, we can develop
more robust methods
for aligning AI with human values,
preparing for the
challenges posed by future
superintelligent systems. For example,
scalable
oversight techniques might be used to
generate weak supervision
signals that a strong model will then
learn to
generalize beyond. By combining these
approaches, we can create
more robust protocols for AI alignment for
example, recursive
reward modeling can use Do2SG to train
powerful reward
models with human preference annotations.
Debate combined with W2SG
can train models to generalize human
judgments to new
debates. Task decomposition combined with
W2SG can supervise atomic
tasks with a reward model trained from
human preferences.
Evaluating these techniques in different
settings helps understand their
strengths and weaknesses. In non scheming
settings where models
are not deceptively aligned, classic weak
to strong techniques
and scalable oversight can be directly
compared. In scheming
settings where models might act
adversarially, evaluations need to
consider potential deception providing a
conservative measure of a
protocol's robustness. When there is no
scheming deceptive alignment,
then we can use W2G techniques in a
straightforward
manner through techniques like
sandwiching. However, if we have
scheming deceptively aligned AI, it might
act adversarially. In
this case, we can use proposals like meta
level
adversarial techniques. Both of these are
what we discuss
in the following Sandwiching Evaluation
Sandwiching is an experimental
setup that leverages narrowly superhuman
models to evaluate how
well our oversight techniques work in
controlled settings. The
sandwiching setup contains three primary
layers. 1. Non expert
layer at the bottom we have non experts.
These
are people who wouldn't be able to solve
the
given task independently. As an example,
think of laypeople
being asked to pick stocks or give medical
diagnoses.
These are stand ins for a future version
of
humanity. They need to use the scalable
oversight techniques
to guide the AI's behavior in a more
aligned
direction. 2. AI model in the middle we
have
the narrowly superhuman AI model that we
want to
test the oversight technique on. This
model has some
capabilities that we are unable to elicit.
The non
expert should be able to align the model
by
getting it to display the kind of behavior
we
want using the given scalable oversight
technique. 3. Expert
layer at the top we have domain experts
who
evaluate the success of the alignment
attempt. They serve
as a benchmark providing feedback without
directly interacting with
the non experts or the AI during the
process.
We can also use ground truth labels from
data
sets as replacements for the expert layer
instead of
hiring actual experts. There is figure
8.23 in the
textbook here. Empirical demonstration of
Sandwiching Researchers conducted an
experiment with non experts tasked to
answer multiple choice
questions. The task was to answer multiple
choice questions
from the Measuring Massive Multitask
Language Understanding benchmark. This
benchmark contains hundreds of questions
on math, physics, morality,
ethics and a range of topics. They also
had
to answer questions based on short stories
from quality
benchmark in five minutes. The scalable
oversight technique that
they were given was a simple amplification
using an
AI assistant chatbot. The performance was
measured by using
the correct answer ground truth labels
from the dataset.
When measured individually, the model
outperformed unassisted humans on
both tasks by a large margin. This means
the
basic condition for testing sandwiching
was fulfilled, the model
being better than the non experts. Over
the course
of the experiment, the chatbot assisted
humans got substantially
better scores on the tasks than either the
humans
or the models did alone. Even though this
was
an extremely simplified design, the
participants managed to move
the behavior of the model in the direction
that
we would want, that is make the model more
aligned. So the researchers managed to
effectively demonstrate sandwiching
as an experimental design. Building on
this baseline, future
experiments can evaluate the efficacy of
more complex scalable
oversight methods like retraining, fine
tuning, or debate.